Herbert Benjamin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Herbert Benjamin Papers 1915-2004 (bulk 1923-1982)
MSS85109
Benjamin, Herbert, 1900-1983
3,000 items plus one oversize
14 containers
5.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Communist Party official. Correspondence, memoranda, memoirs and additional writings, notes, printed matter, and other papers primarily relating to Benjamin’s life and his work in the Communist Party, particularly his activities as a leader in the organized unemployed movement during the 1930s.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Benjamin, Herbert, 1900-1983.
Organizations
Communist Party of the United States of America.; Industrial Workers of the World.; National Hunger March (1st: 1931: Washington, D.C.); National Hunger March (2nd: 1932: Washington, D.C.); National Unemployment Council.; Workers Alliance of America.
Subjects
Communism--Michigan.; Communism--New York (State); Communism--Ohio.; Communism--Pennsylvania.; Communism--United States.; Depressions--1929--United States.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Unemployed--United States.
Places
United States--Economic conditions--1918-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.
Provenance
The papers of Herbert Benjamin, Communist Party official, were given to the Library of Congress by his son, Ernst Benjamin, in 2004.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Herbert Benjamin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1900, Dec. 17 Born Benjamin Grefenson, Effingham, Ill.
1919 Joined Industrial Workers of the World
1920 Married Jennie Cooperman
1921 Joined Communist Party of America, Erie, Pa.
1923 1931 Held positions in Communist Party districts in New York, Ohio, and Pennsylvania
1928 Became national committee member, Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA)
1931 Named national organizer of unemployed for the CPUSA Led National Hunger March to Washington, D.C.
1931 1935 National secretary, Unemployed Councils
1932 Led second National Hunger March to Washington, D.C.
1935 1940 General secretary-treasurer, Workers Alliance of America
193? Married Lillian Gerber
1940 Conducted a national “party building tour” to promote the CPUSA
1940 1942 General executive board member and national executive secretary, International Workers Order
1942 1944 Head of Communist Party in Missouri
194[?] 195[?] Owner and operator, Metropolitan News Agency, Washington, D.C. Manager, Trenton Terrace Apartments, Washington, D.C.
1953 1978 Merchant, Pottery Fair, Washington, D.C.
1983, May 10 Died, Rockville, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Herbert Benjamin (1900-1983) span the years 1915-2004, with the bulk of the material dating from 1923 to 1982. They are arranged as general correspondence, subject files, writings, and oversize. A large portion of the collection relates to Benjamin’s activities as a member of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) from 1921 to 1944, particularly his work as a leader of the organized unemployed movement during the 1930s.
The most detailed information about Herbert Benjamin’s life as a communist in the 1920s and 1930s is in his unfinished autobiography, “Memoirs of an Indelible Red,” filed in the writings section. Benjamin devoted the last decade of his life to writing and rewriting his autobiography. In his drafts, Benjamin described the experiences that led him to join the Industrial Workers of the World and then the Communist Party. He recounts his attendance at the 1922 Communist Party convention in Bridgman, Michigan; his work in Buffalo, Cleveland, and New York, and in Philadelphia, Reading, and Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania; his leadership of the first and second National Hunger marches on Washington, D.C., in 1931 and 1932; the work to organize the unemployed during the Depression; and the circumstances which led him to end his public association with the CPUSA. The writings also contain Benjamin’s statements of his political beliefs and personal reassessments over four decades.
Subject files contain records of the organizations in which Benjamin worked on behalf of the unemployed in the 1930s, including the National Unemployment Council, the Unemployed Councils, and the Workers Alliance of America. Files of the CPUSA relate to Benjamin’s nationwide speaking tour in 1940 for the purpose of “party building.” Subject files compiled in later years on people, issues, and current events often include Benjamin’s thoughts on the topics. Files on “Historians” document Benjamin’s contact with historians in the 1970s and his reaction to historical assessments of the organized unemployed movement in the 1930s.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - Darcy, Sam A., 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Family members, 1956-1959, 1968, 1982-1983, 1994, undated (Box 1)
  - Gordon, Max, 1974-1983, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondents, 1954-1956, 1965-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Rosenzweig, Roy, 1972-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Sargent, James E., 1981-1982 (Box 1)
- Subject files (Box 1)
  - China versus USSR, 1960-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Communist Party of the United States of America (Box 1)
    - Miscellany, 1923-1924, 1943-1946, ca. 1965, 1976-1981, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Notebooks, 192[?], 194[?] (Box 2)
    - Speaking tour (Box 2)
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1940 (Box 2)
      - Fliers and handbills, 1940 (Box 2)
      - Miscellany, 1940, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Notes, 1940, undated (Box 2)
      - Press clippings, 1940, undated (Box 2)
    - Unemployment, 1928-1938, 1951, 1961, undated (Box 2)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Fagin, Sophia (niece) (Box 2)
    - Fliers and handbills, 1939-1941, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Miscellany, 1939-1941, 2004, undated (Box 2)
  - Freedom of Information Act requests, 1976-1978, undated (Box 3)
  - Historians, 1974-1976, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Howe, Irving, and Lewis Coser, The American Communist Party, 1957, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Hunger marches, 1930-1933, 1956, 1973, 1981-1982, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - International Workers Order, 1940-1942, undated, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - Interview for Source, Inc., 1976 (Box 4)
  - Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1960-1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellany (Box 4)
    - 1915, 1921-1932, 1940-1947, 1953-1974, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1975-1982, undated See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - National Conference on New Politics, Chicago, Ill., 1967-1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - National Unemployment Council, 1934-1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - New American Movement, 1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - New Deal, 1933-1941, 1965, 1973, undated (Box 5)
  - Poland, 1981-1982, undated (Box 6)
  - Political demonstrations, 1967-1978, undated (Box 6)
  - Poor People’s March, 1968-1972, undated (Box 6)
  - Radical archives project, 1966-1968, 1975, undated (Box 6)
  - Social security (Box 6)
    - Correspondence regarding Benjamin’s project, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Notes, undated (Box 6)
    - Press clippings, 1975-1983, undated (Box 6)
    - Writings and reflections, 1982-1983, undated (Box 6)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E. (1900-1965), 1958-1959, undated (Box 6)
  - Unemployed Councils (Box 6)
    - Gallup, N. Mex., 1933-1934, 1965, undated (Box 6)
    - General, 1931-1934, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Unemployment and social insurance, 1933-1935, 1977, undated (Box 6)
  - Unification of unemployed organizations, 1935-1936, undated For additional material see same container, Workers Alliance of America (Box 7)
  - Unitarian-Universalist Fellowship of Huntington, Huntington, Long Island, N. Y., 1977-1978, undated (Box 7)
  - Vietnam War, 1967-1968, undated (Box 7)
  - Viewpoint Publishing Group, 1977-1978, undated (Box 7)
  - Violence and militancy, 1967-1969, undated (Box 7)
  - Workers Alliance of America (Box 7)
    - 1935-1938, (7 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1939-1942, 1951, 1980-1982, undated, (6 folders) (Box 8)
- Writings (Box 8)
  - Letters to editors 1933, 1960, 1968-1973, 1979-1980, undated (Box 8)
  - Memoirs (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1983, undated (Box 8)
    - Drafts (Box 8)
      - Outlines, 1965, 1977-1978, undated (Box 8)
      - Preface, undated (Box 8)
      - Section 1, prologue, boyhood, 1973-1983, undated, (5 folders) (Box 9)
      - Section 2, riding the rails and hobo life, 1965, 1979, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Section 3, Erie, Pa., undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Section 4, Industrial Workers of the World, undated, (4 folders) (Box 10)
      - Section 5, communist underground, 1964-1965, 1976-1978, undated, (5 folders) (Box 10)
      - Section 6, Cleveland, Ohio, Reading, Pa., Wilkes-Barre, Pa., 1965, 1978, undated (Box 11)
      - Section 7, factional leader, 1978-1979, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Section 8, “Sacco and Vanzetti Must Not Die,” undated (Box 11)
      - Section 9, Philadelphia, Pa., district, 1976, undated, (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - Section 10, New York in the early stage of the Depression, 1975-1979, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Section 11, Cleveland, Ohio, and USSR, 1975-1979, undated (Box 11)
      - Section 12, first National Hunger March, 1973-1981, undated, (6 folders) (Box 12)
      - Section 13, between hunger marches, 1981-1982, undated, (4 folders) (Box 12)
      - Section 14, second National Hunger March, 1981, undated (Box 13)
      - Section 15, New Deal, 1982 (Box 13)
      - Section 16, concluding chapter, 1965, 1976, undated (Box 13)
      - Unidentified, 1979, undated (Box 13)
    - Illustrations, 1931-1932, 1969, undated (Box 13)
    - Miscellany, 1973-1978, undated (Box 13)
    - Research notes, 1936, 1973-1976, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 13)
    - 1932-1940, 1959-1975, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1976-1982, undated (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - Notes and jottings, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Statements of personal political beliefs, 1944[?]-1957, 1965-1973, 1982-1983, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Miscellany, undated (Container 5) (Box OV 1)